A Guide to the Library of Virginia Replevin Files, 1908-1993
Library of Virginia
Library of Virginia
The Library of Virginia Replevin Files, 1908-1993
The Library of Virginia
34931
38634
40399
2 cu. ft. (3 boxes)
Office of the State Archivist
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
Accessions were transferred by the office of the State Archivist. 34931 is an accumulation of accessions relating to replevin. 38634 was transferred 11/16/2001. 40399 was transferred 3/18/2003.
Related Material
Local Government Replevin Records, Accession 41209, consists of local records that were removed by Larry Vass from the collection.
Executive Papers and other state records removed by Larry Vass have been refiled with their original collections.
Biographical Information
Replevin is a legal remedy through which property is returned after being unlawfully obtained in some manner. Under the Virginia Public Records Act, public records never cease being public records until they are destroyed. Because of this, the Library of Virginia has initiated or facilitated several cases of replevin throughout the years. Cases were resolved either before involving the legal system, or through court cases. Notable instances in this collection include the Lossing collection, the Journal of the Virginia Convention of May 1776, Larry I. Vass v. Virginia, as well as proceedings against Jack Hamilton in Middlesex and Isle of Wight counties.
Scope and Content
These collections document the replevin actions taken by the Library of Virginia and the Office of the State Archivist. It also includes cases from county Circuit Courts for which the Library of Virginia stepped in and played an active role in proceedings. Records include correspondence, research, archival transfer receipts, stack slips, pamphlets, newspaper articles, inventory forms, as well as court records such as transcripts, depositions, judgments, and other related records.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged into 11 series, chronologically by replevin case.
Series I: Lossing v. Virginia (1908-1914)
Series II: James L. Hook (1941-1942)
Series III: Miscellaneous (1949-1964)
Series IV: The Rosenbach Company (1949-1950)
Series V: Duke University (1950)
Series VI: Charlotte County v. Bloxom, Curtis (1971, 1976-1980)
Series VII: Larry I. Vass v. Virginia (1911-1913, bulk 1967-1973)
Series VIII: Alexandria v. Yudkin (1976-1977)
Series IX: David F. Zullo (1986)
Series X: Middlesex County v. Hamilton (1977, bulk 1991-1993)
Series XI: Isle of Wight v. Hamilton (1991-1993)
Contents List
- Replevin Records, 1908-1993., Extent: 3 boxes.
  - Series I: Lossing v. Virginia, 1908-1914. (Box 1, Folder 1-4)
    This series documents the actions taken to obtain state records from the estate of Benson Lossing. It includes research, newspaper articles, board resolutions, and correspondence between the Library and the auction house.
    - Replevin Articles, 1908-1912. (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Correspondence, 1911-1914. (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Board Resolutions, 1912-1913. (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Newspaper Articles, 1912. (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Series II: James L. Hook, 1941-1942. (Box 1, Folder 5)
    This series documents the reacquisition of the Journal of the Virginia Convention of May 1776 from James Hook. The records are chiefly correspondence, detailing Hook's initial offer, a concerned citizen's attempts to intervene, the assessment of the book by Colonial Williamsburg, and the seizure of the item by the Library.
    - Correspondence, 1941-1942. (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Series III: Miscellaneous, 1949-1964. (Box 1)
    This series documents miscellaneous replevin related records in the collection including correspondence, lists of Virginia state records, and mug shots.
    - Authorizing Replevin Funds, 1949. (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Lists of Virginia Records, Undated, 1950-1951. (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Mug shot of Wilfred H. Marty, 1964. (Box 1, Folder 11)
      Mug shots of Wilfred H. Marty who was arrested in the fall of 1964 for attempted theft of "two valuable Confederate volumes" from the Library.
  - Series IV: The Rosenbach Company, 1949-1950. (Box 1)
    This series documents the replevin actions taken by the Library of Virginia with the Rosenbach auction company. Records include auction catalogs and correspondence regarding the removal of records.
    - The History of America in Documents, 1949-1950. (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Correspondence, 1949-1950. (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Series V: Duke University, 1950. (Box 1, Folder 9)
    This series documents the discussion between Duke University and the Library of Virginia for the return of records. This series contains correspondence.
    - Correspondence, 1950. (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Series VI: Charlotte County v. Bloxom and Curtis, 1971, 1978-1980. (Box 1, Folder 12-14)
    This series documents the case against Bloxom and Curtis by Charlotte County Circuit Court for the return of records. This series includes a records survey and lists of records, newspaper articles, correspondence, and the case judgement.
    - List of Records and Records Survey, 1971. (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Charlotte County Gazette Articles, 1976. (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Correspondence and Judgement, 1978-1980. (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Series VII: Larry Vass v. Virginia (Accessions 40399, 34931), 1911-1913, 1967-1973. (Boxes 1 (34931), 1 (40399))
    This series documents the trial of the case of the Commonwealth v.. Larry Ivan Vass for the theft of documents from the Virginia State Library and Archives between 1969 and 1972. Records include correspondence, lists of stolen documents, stack slips, patron registers, photocopy orders, receipt forms, subpoenas, court records, and other related documents.
    The stolen state records have been removed from Accession 40399 and refiled with their original collection, and local records are now housed under Accession 41209.
    - Archival Receipts, 1972. (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Correspondence, 1967, 1972-1973. (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - National Historic Preservation Commission Photocopy Orders, 1969. (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Notes and Lists, 1972-1973. (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Patron Register, 1970-1972. (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Stack Slips, 1969-1972. (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Court Transcript (Accession 34931), 1972. (Box 1, Folder 15-17)
    - Stolen Documents, 1911-1913, 1972-1973. (Folder 7-9)
      - List of Stolen Documents, 1972-1973. (Box 1, Folder 7)
      - Allason Papers, 1911-1913, 1972-1973. (Box 1, Folder 8)
      - Executive Papers, 1972. (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Series VIII: City of Alexandria v. Yudkin, 1976-1977. (Box 1, Folder 18-20)
    This series documents the replevin case by the City of Alexandria against Yudkin, which the Library of Virginia took part in. This series consists of court documents, correspondence, and a survey of historical records.
    - Court Documents, 1976-1977. (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - Correspondence, 1976-1977. (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - Historical Records Survey, 1977. (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Series IX: David F. Zullo, 1986. (Box 1, Folder 21)
    This series documents the replevin of records from seller David Zullo, who was selling records on consignment from a private collector. Records include correspondence between Zullo, the Library, and the consigner, as well as item lists.
    - Correspondence and Item Lists, 1986. (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Series X: Middlesex County v. Jack Hamilton (Accession 34931, 38634), 1977, 1991-1993. (Box 1 (38634), 1 (34931), Folder 1-5, 22-35)
    This series documents the case brought against bookseller Jack Hamilton by Middlesex County Circuit Court for the return of records. Records include correspondence, document inventories, newspaper articles, as well as court documents including depositions, opinions, court transcripts, as well as final judgments.
    - Local Record Inventory Forms (38634), 1977. (Box 1, Folder 1-4)
    - Correspondence and ARC Receipts (38634), 1991. (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Correspondence, 1991-1993. (Box 1, Folder 22)
    - Document Inventories, 1991. (Box 1, Folder 23)
    - Petition to Intervene, 1991. (Box 1, Folder 24)
    - Deposition of Dan Gill and Lyndon Hart, 1991. (Box 1, Folder 25)
    - Deposition of Dr. Louis Manarin, 1991. (Box 1, Folder 26)
    - Interrogatories, 1991. (Box 1, Folder 27)
    - Proceedings, 1991. (Box 1, Folder 28)
    - Attorney General's Opinion, 1991. (Box 1, Folder 29)
    - Proceedings, 1991. (Box 1, Folder 30)
    - Publications, 1991-1993. (Box 1, Folder 31)
    - Proceedings, 1992. (Box 1, Folder 32)
    - Respondent's Memorandum, 1992. (Box 1, Folder 33)
    - Petitioner's Reply, 1992. (Box 1, Folder 34)
    - Judgement, 1992. (Box 1, Folder 35)
    - Judgement, 1992. (Box 1, Folder 36)
    - Dismissal and Receipt, 1993. (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - Series XI: Isle of Wight County v. Jack Hamilton (Accession 34931, 38634), 1991-1993. (Box 1 (38634), 1 (34931), Folder 6, 36-37)
    This series documents the case -brought against bookseller Jack Hamilton by Isle of Wight County Circuit Court for the return of records. This case was resolved not long after the judgement was made in Middlesex County v. Hamilton. Records include correspondence, ARC receipts, court records, and publications.
    - Correspondence and ARC Receipts, 1991-1993. (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Correspondence and Court Records, 1991-1993. (Box 1, Folder 36)
    - Virginia Public Records Act Declared Constitutional, 1993. (Box 1, Folder 37)